Mss.B.Sca42
American Philosophical Society
Scaliger family papers, fifteenth-nineteenth centuries
1459-1862 January 25
Mss.B.Sca42
American Philosophical Society
1.5 Linear feet Ca. 330 items
The Scaliger Family Papers, when taken together, trace the history of a noble family that was originally from Italy but lived primarily in Agen, France from the mid-1500s through the mid-1800s. Beginning with the patriarch, Julius Caesar Scaliger (1484-1558), a celebrated Italian scholar and physician, the members of the Scaliger family upheld an illustrious reputation over the centuries as scholars, military leaders, and noblemen. Throughout their family’s history, the Scaligers maintained that they were descended from the Della Scallas, Princes of Verona. It is as a result of the necessity to defend this claim as well as later attempts to prove their ties to their noble heritage that this collection of documents has remained so well intact. The Scaliger Family Papers is a collection that encompasses several different kinds of documents that span from 1539 to 1862 including letters, genealogical material, works by members of the Scaliger family, as well as military, legal, and financial documents.
Scaliger Family.
Box 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Cécile Poizat, 1888; accessioned, 1900.
Biographical/Historical note
The Scaliger Family Papers, when taken together, trace the history of a noble family that was originally from Italy but lived primarily in Agen, France from the mid-1500s through the mid-1800s. Beginning with the patriarch, Julius Caesar Scaliger (1484-1558), a celebrated Italian scholar and physician, the members of the Scaliger family upheld an illustrious reputation over the centuries as scholars, military leaders, and noblemen. Throughout their family’s history, the Scaligers maintained that they were descended from the Della Scallas, Princes of Verona. It is perhaps as a result of the necessity to defend this claim as well as later attempts to prove ties to their noble heritage that this collection of papers has remained so well intact. This, in part, helps to explain why Mademoiselle Victoire de Vérone, the last surviving legitimate heir of the Scaliger family, still possessed the papers of her family dating back as early as the 1530s even though she was living in poverty.
In order to truly understand this collection it is important to first consider the founder of the family, Julius Caesar Scaliger. Over the course of his lifetime, Julius Caesar Scaliger engaged in a wide variety of pursuits. According to his own account, he began as a page in the court of Emperor Maximilian. From there, he became a soldier and was later even knighted for several acts of bravery. But, it was not for his military career that Scaliger was best known. It was rather his work as a scholar and physician that garnered him the most fame. As a young man Scaliger moved from Italy to Agen, a small town in the south of France. It was in Agen that he established a school, built a medical practice, and started a family. Overtime, Scaliger’s medical teachings became well-known as part of a revolt against strict adherence to ancient writings. He also became famous for his poetry as well as an oration he wrote violently denouncing the work of Erasmus. During the last years of his life, Scaliger worked on his most well-known book, Poetics. Published after his death, this book marked the first attempt to develop a philosophical theory of poetry. Julius Caesar Scaliger died on October 28, 1558, leaving behind a powerful legacy for his family to follow.
Despite Julius Caesar Scaliger’s profound accomplishments, his son, Joseph Juste Scaliger (1540-1609), is considered to have eclipsed his father’s fame with his work as a religious leader and scholar known for expanding the commonly held notions of classical history. It was Joseph Juste Scaliger who publically forwarded the claim that his family was descended from the Princes of Verona in his book Epistola de Vetustate et Splendore Gentis Scaligerae et J.C. Scaligeri Vita. He was attacked for this supposition and responded in later books to defend his claims to nobility, a practice his family would continue most notably in the 1660s and 1670s.
Nobility afforded many privileges in France during the seventeenth century and, as a result, many people began to issue false claims of noble birth. Consequently, King Louis XIV issued a declaration in 1666 requiring a verification of noble titles throughout the realm. In response, Joseph de Charrier de Lescale de Vérone (?-1689), head of the Scaliger family at the time, began to collect proof of the nobility of his ancestors and therefore himself. It is this necessity to verify the nobility of his lineage that is perhaps what brought this collection of papers together in the first place. As a result of his extensive compilation of documents as well as a series of numbered letters stating his claims, not only did the king accept Joseph’s petition for nobility, but also he officially recognized the Lescales of Verona as descendants of the Princes of Verona, as Joseph Juste Scaliger had asserted more than fifty years before.
In 1847 the last surviving heir of the Scaliger family legacy, Victoire de Vérone, was living destitute and alone in the same château in Agen that Julius Caesar Scaliger had originally built to house his growing family more than three hundred years before. Resigned to a life of poverty, it came as a shock to Victoire when she received a visit from Monsieur Jean Robert Poizat (1803-1868)who claimed that he was distantly related to her and, as a result, also a descendant of the Scaliger family. It appears that Victoire’s father had left his family in France to look after his wife’s property in Santo Domingo. There, unbeknownst to his wife in France, he had developed a relationship with another woman from which two children were born one being Jean Robert Poizat’s mother making Poizat, albeit distantly and illegitimately, related to Victoire. In return for the promise of money, Jean Robert Poizat requested the papers and documents of the Scaliger family in order to obtain official recognition of his lineage. Victoire, desperate for financial aid, agreed and, following a series of letters, the papers of the Scaliger family, collected since the mid-1500s, changed hands.
Scope and Contents note
This collection encompasses several different kinds of documents that span from the mid-1500s through the mid-1800s including letters, genealogical material, works by members of the Scaliger family, as well as military, legal, and financial documents.
There are three broad categories of correspondence within the collection. The first is a series of letters dating from 1609 to 1735. They are all addressed to Monsieur de Vérone a agen but because it is such an ambiguous title it is unclear specifically which member of the family the letter belongs to. As a result, this group of letters is from several different senders, in markedly different handwritings, and probably intended for different people. The second category of correspondence is the letters of Joseph de Charrier de Lescale de Vérone (?-1689). The bulk of these letters are a numbered correspondence whereby Joseph verifies his claims to the Lescale name supported by the legal documents he amassed as proof. The final group of correspondence is addressed to Jean Robert Poizat (1803-1868) and records his attempts to obtain recognition of his lineage through support from Victoire de Vérone and the validation of the Count de Magne of the College of Heralds.
Genealogical material represents another important component of this collection. It includes notes and lists, family trees, and drawings of family crests. These documents trace fragments of the lineage of not only the Scaligers but also other families closely related to them such as the Montaults, Monmejans, and the Bousquets. These connections, especially as they represent the ties to nobility, are further reinforced throughout the rest of the collection especially within the military, legal, and financial documents.
The works by members of the Scaliger family also reflect this preoccupation with family ancestry and many of the works record the history of the family and question its origins. These often sewn together sheaths of paper synthesize the genealogical notes and drawings as well as the legal documents that marked the passing of arms and noble titles through wills and marriage certificates.
The final and most varied series of documents within the collection are the military, legal, and financial documents, which includes contracts, death certificates, wills, orders from the King of France, agreements, marriage contracts, baptism certificates, and even the receipt for the shipment of the case of documents containing the Scaliger family papers from Mademoiselle Victoire de Vérone in Agen to Jean Robert Poizat in Paris. It is these documents that officially verify the connections, suppositions, and rights asserted within the correspondence, genealogical notes, and works by the members of the Scaliger family.
General note
See also: article by Warren E. Blake: Joseph Justus Scaliger, pp. 83-91 (The Classical Journal, Vol. 36, No. 2, November 1940)
article by Vernon Hall, Jr: Scaliger Family Papers, pp.120-123 (Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society, Vol. 92, No.2, Studies of Historical Documents in the Library of the American Philosophical Society, May 5 1948)
article by Vernon Hall, Jr: Life of Julius Caesar Scaliger (1484-1558), pp. 85-170 (Transactions of the American Philosophical Society, New Series, Vol. 40, No. 2, 1950)
book by George W. Robinson: Autobiography of Joseph Scaliger (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1927)
African American History note
Poizat family manuscripts, which include lists of slaves in Santo Domingo and baptismal certificates, may be of interest to scholars of African American history.
Early American History note
This large collection contains the family papers of the Scaligers, a prominent French family that eventually immigrated to Philadelphia in the mid-nineteenth century. The collection contains a wealth of information on the history and genealogy of this family. Some of the documents date to the fifteenth century. There is a notable amount of documents from the seventeenth and nineteenth centuries. The portion of the collection from the earlier period is mostly composed of legal documents. The nineteenth century documents are mostly correspondence. All of the documents appear to be in French or Latin. Most of these documents are beyond the scope of the early American guide, but there are some documents from Santo Domingo that relate to the family’s interest in a slave plantation there.
Scaliger, Joseph Juste, 1540-1609; Scaligero, Giulio Cesare, 1484-1558; African American; Agen (France); Beyond Early America; Certificates.; Contracts -- France -- History.; Correspondence.; Family Correspondence; France -- Colonies.; France -- History.; France -- Intellectual life.; France -- Social life and customs -- 15th century; France -- Social life and customs -- 16th century.; France -- Social life and customs -- 17th century.; France -- Social life and customs -- 18th century.; Genealogies.; Immigrants--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia; Legal Records; Marriage and Family Life; Marriage certificates.; Marriage customs and rites -- France -- History.; Military -- France -- History.; Miscellaneous; Nobility -- France.; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- History.; Slaves -- Dominican Republic -- Santo Domingo.; Slaves, slavery, slave trade; Wills.
- Series I. Correspondence, 1609 July 4-1862 January 25; 122.0 folders
  - Subseries A. de Verone a agen letters, 1609 July 4-1735 November 25; 13.0 folders
    Scope and Contents note
    This is a series of letters dating from 1609 to 1735. While they are all addressed to Monsieur de Verone a agen, it is an ambiguous title making it unclear specifically which member of the family the letter belongs to. As a result, they are from several different senders and probably intended for several different people.
    Scaliger
    - Letter to Monsieur de Verone from Monsieur de Calais de Bourdeause, 1609 July 4; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 1)
      This letter is addressed to Monsieur de Verone a agen.
    - Letter to Monsieur de Verone from Monsieur de Calais de Bourdeause, 1609 August 6; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale, 1650 May 24; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter from Prince Thomas de Savoye to de S'Escalle, 16 November 1647; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Prince Thomas of Savoye is noted as being General of the Armies of the King in Itlay and the letter is addressed to de S'Escalle Lientent au regiment de Normandie. Both Joseph Juste de Charrier de Lescale de Vérone and his son Joseph de Charrier de Lescale de Vérone served in the military so it is likely that the letter was intended for either one of them.
    - 11 lettres de Vierneury et nombreux fragnements de lettres du meme sans date, 1670s; 26.0 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
      There are 26 individual pieces of paper within a more modern looking lined paper folder that reads "No. 10: 11 lettres de Viereury et nombreux fraguements de lettres du meme sans date."
    - Letter to Monsieur de Verone, 1676 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      This letter is addressed to Monsieur de Verone a agen, guienne par paris.
    - Pas très important- series of notes and letters, 1678-1792; 21.0 items (Box 1, Folder 7)
      This is a set of 21 individual pieces of paper that seem to be letters mostly addressed to Monsieur de Verone a agen. Joseph de Charrier de Vérone is mentioned specifically in a few of the letters but not all may be about or for him. There are also smaller pieces of paper with notes on them. All of these papers are inside of a folder made of a more modern looking white lined piece of paper that reads "No 7 pas très important."
      Charrier de Lescale de Vérone, Joseph de, -1689; Scaliger
    - Letter to Monsieur de Verone, 1689 October 19; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letter to Monsieur de Verone, 1690 April 7; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letter to Monsieur de Verone, 1694 April 16; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letter to Monsieur Lescale de Verone, 1699 July 1; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 11)
      This letter is addressed to Monsieur Lescale de Verone a agen par Bourdeaux.
    - Letter to Monseiur de Veronne, 1706; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale de Verone, 1735 November 25; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 13)
      This letter is addressed to Monsieur de Lescale de Verone a agen pres les cordeliers, a montagnae.
  - Subseries B. Joseph de Charrier de Lescale de Vérone letters, 1652 April 1-1673 August 28; 50.0 folders; Charrier de Lescale de Vérone, Joseph de, -1689
    - Letter to Monsieur de Lescalle from a cousin, January 20; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 14)
      This letter is addressed to Monsieur de Lescalle capitene au regiment de candalle agen. Because it mentions Monsieur de Lescalle as Captain of the Candal Regiment it must be addressed to Joseph de Charrier de Lescale de Vérone who held that postion.
      Charrier de Lescale de Vérone, Joseph de, -1689
    - Letter to Monsieur de Lescalle from a cousin, January 20; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Letter about Captain de Lescale to Monsieur le Comte d'Harcour, 1652 April 1; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Because this letter mentions Monsieur de Lescalle as Captain of the Candal Regiment it must be addressed to Joseph de Charrier de Lescale de Vérone who held that postion.
    - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale, 1654 May 12; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 17)
      This letter is addressed to Monsieur de Lescalle Premier Cappitaine et Comandant du Regiment d'Infenterie de Candale. Because it mentions Monsieur de Lescalle as Captain of the Candale Regiment it must be addressed to Joseph de Charrier de Lescale de Vérone who held that postion.
    - Subsubseries A. Individually numbered letters, 1666 March 11-1673 August 28; 44.0 items
      Note: letters numbered 3 and 4 are missing so as a result there are 44 numbered letters in total
      These are a series of numbered letters written by Joseph de Charrier de Lescale de Verone (great, great grandson of Julius Ceasar Scaliger) in support of his claims to the Lescale name. According to Vernon Hall Jr in his essay, The Scaliger Family Papers, these claims fell into three broad categories: (1) that he had borne arms for the King and recieved a commission in the regiment of Candal and that further his father too had borne arms in the armies of the king; (2) that the house of Lescale de Verone decended from the Princes of Verona; (3) that he had the right to the name of Lescale for he legally recieved it through his father from his grandmother, Anne de Lescale. The addresses on the letters vary slightly over time and are noted in the Scope and Contents note.
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescalle- number 1, 1666 March 11; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 18)
        This letter is addressed to Monsieur de Lescalle a agen.
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescalle- number 2, 1666 June 7; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescalle- number 5, 1670 July 20; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescalle- number 6, 1670 July 20; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescalle- number 7, 1671 January 18; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescalle- number 8, 1671 March 1; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Letter to Monsieur des anges- number 9, 1671 August 18; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 24)
        The address on this letter is difficult to read but appears to say: Monsieur des anges Escuyer dans la maison ou chez Madame de Girles ou Monsieur de Lesca a agen.
      - Letter number 10, 1671 September 7; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 25)
        This letter does not have an address.
      - Letter number 11, 1671 September 12; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Letter number 12, 1671 September 14; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Letter to Monsieur des anges- number 13, 1671 September 15; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 28)
        The address on this letter is difficult to read but appears to say: Monsieur des anges Escuyer dans la maison a agen.
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 14, 1671 October 3; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 29)
        This letter is addressed to Monsieur de Lescale Escuyer dans sa maison a agen.
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 15, 1671 October 27; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 16, 1671 November 14; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 17, 1671 November 17; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 18, 1671 December 19; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 19, 1671 December 26; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Letter number 20, 1672 January 1; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 21, 1672 January 2; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 36)
        These letters are addressed to Monsieur de Lescale Escuyer dans sa maison a agen.
      - Letter to Monsieur des anges- number 22, 1672 January 18; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 37)
        The address on this letter is difficult to read but appears to say: Monsieur des anges Escuyer dans sa maison a agen.
      - Letter number 23, 1672 February 6; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 24, 1672 March 6; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 39)
        The address on this letter reads Monsieur de Lescale Escuyer dans sa maison a agen.
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 25, 1672 April 1; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 26, 1672 June 7; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - Letter number 27, 1672 June 19; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 28, 1672 August 17; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 43)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 29, 1672 August 31; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 30, 1672 September 24; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 31, 1672 Ocrtober 12; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 46)
        The address on this letter reads Monsieur de Lescale Escuyer a agen.
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 32, 1672 November 26; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 33, 1672 December 7; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 34, 1672 December 14; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 49)
      - Letter number 35, 1673 January 22; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 36, 1673 February 19; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 51)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 37, 1673 March 5; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 52)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 38, 1673 April 18; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 53)
      - Letter to Monsieur desanges- number 39, 1673 June 17; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 54)
        The address on this letter is difficult to read but appears to say: Monsieur desanges Escuyer dans sa maison a agen.
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 40, 1673 June 26; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 55)
      - Letter to Monsieur desanges- number 41, 1673 June 29; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 56)
      - Letter number 42, 1673 July 18; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 57)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 43, 1673 August 2; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 58)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 44, 1673 August 6; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 59)
      - Letter to Monsieur de Lescale- number 45, 1673 August 20; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 60)
      - Letter number 46, 1673 August 28; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Receuil de letres très importante, 1666 March 11-1683 August 25; 1.0 item; Charrier de Lescale de Vérone, Joseph de, -1689 (Box Oversize 1, Folder 1)
      This is a rewritten version (presumably by Joseph de Charrier de Lescale de Vérone) of the individually numbered letters tied together into a book.
      This document can be found in Oversize Box 1.
    - Receuil de lettres très importante- transcription, undated; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 62)
      This is a transcription of Receuil de lettres très important--the rewritten version of the series of numbered letters. It is written on plain paper and looks more modern especially since the handwriting seems to match that of other, more modern writing.
  - Letter to Monseiur de montmejan, 1672 January 9; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 63)
    The address on this letter reads Monseiur de montmejan advocat a agen
    Monmejan, Francois de; Monmejan
  - Letter to Monsieur Francois de Montmejan, 1688 January; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 64)
    The address on this letter reads Monsieur Francois de Montmejan advocat ade en parlement
  - Letter from Montaut, 1766 July 29; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 65)
    Montault
  - Letter from l'abbé, 1766 August 7; 1.0 item (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Subseries C. Jean Robert Poizat letters, 1843 October 27-1860 January 28; 53.0 folders
    As Vernon Hall Jr. writes in his essay, The Scaliger Family Papers, "This is a series of letters which passed between the last of the true Scaligers, Mlle Victoire de Vérone and Monsieur and Madame Poizat of the illegitimate branch. These letters tell the story of the transfer of documents to the hands of the Poizats, Mlle Victoire's pathetic appeals for financial aid, and the history of the Poizats' efforts through the Count de Magne of the College of Heralds to obtain recognition of their pretentions."
    Poizat, Jean Robert, 1803-1868 July 18